<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Dayda</title>
  <updated>2021-02-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <link rel="self" href="http://localhost:4000/atom.xml"/>
  <author><name>Kin Lane</name></author>
  <id>http://localhost:4000/atom.xml</id>
	<entry>
    <title>Vegetation Data Ground plots, taxon specific - Land Cover Mapping, North Slope of the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge, Alaska, 2019</title>
    <link href="http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/vegetation-data-ground-plots-taxon-specific-land-cover-mapping-north-slope-of-the-arctic-national-wildlife-refuge-alaska-2019.html"/>
    <updated>2021-02-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <content><![CDATA[The resource contains vegetation cover data from the ABR, Inc. – Environmental Research and Services (ABR) 2019 ground surveys plots and the 1987-1992 U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service plots from Jorgenson et al. (1994). Plant taxonomy names have been standardized to ABR accepted taxonomy as described in the North Slope ANWR Land Cover mapping report.

The data in this resource relates to the other data deliverable resources through the project_id and plot_id fields.
]]></content>
    <id>http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/vegetation-data-ground-plots-taxon-specific-land-cover-mapping-north-slope-of-the-arctic-national-wildlife-refuge-alaska-2019.html</id>
  </entry><entry>
    <title>Vegetation Data Ground plots, functional groups - Land Cover Mapping, North Slope of the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge, Alaska, 2019</title>
    <link href="http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/vegetation-data-ground-plots-functional-groups-land-cover-mapping-north-slope-of-the-arctic-national-wildlife-refuge-alaska-2019.html"/>
    <updated>2021-02-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <content><![CDATA[The resource contains the vegetation structure data from the ABR, Inc. – Environmental Research and Services (ABR) 2019 ground surveys plots and the 2013 Alaska Ecoscience Hula Hula &amp;amp; Dalton Hwy dataset. The 1987-1992 U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service plots from Jorgenson et al. (1994) have little to no data in this table. These plots are included here because this table relates to the veg_cover table on project_id and plot_id and therefore must be included to satisfy the database constraints.

The data in this resource relates to the other data deliverable resources through the project_id and plot_id fields.
]]></content>
    <id>http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/vegetation-data-ground-plots-functional-groups-land-cover-mapping-north-slope-of-the-arctic-national-wildlife-refuge-alaska-2019.html</id>
  </entry><entry>
    <title>Vegetation Data Aerial survey plots, taxon specific - Land Cover Mapping, North Slope of the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge, Alaska, 2019</title>
    <link href="http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/vegetation-data-aerial-survey-plots-taxon-specific-land-cover-mapping-north-slope-of-the-arctic-national-wildlife-refuge-alaska-2019.html"/>
    <updated>2021-02-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <content><![CDATA[The resource contains vegetation cover data from the ABR, Inc. – Environmental Research and Services (ABR) 2019 aerial surveys.

The data in this resource relates to the other data deliverable resources through the project_id and plot_id fields.
]]></content>
    <id>http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/vegetation-data-aerial-survey-plots-taxon-specific-land-cover-mapping-north-slope-of-the-arctic-national-wildlife-refuge-alaska-2019.html</id>
  </entry><entry>
    <title>Vegetation Data Aerial survey plots, functional groups - Land Cover Mapping, North Slope of the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge, Alaska, 2019</title>
    <link href="http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/vegetation-data-aerial-survey-plots-functional-groups-land-cover-mapping-north-slope-of-the-arctic-national-wildlife-refuge-alaska-2019.html"/>
    <updated>2021-02-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <content><![CDATA[The resource contains vegetation and general environment data from the ABR, Inc. – Environmental Research and Services (ABR) 2019 aerial surveys. The ABR 2019 ground survey and the 1987-1992 U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service plots from Jorgenson et al. (1994) are also included with cover values converted to top cover. See “abr_anwr_ns_lc_els_deliverable.csv” for general environment data for the ABR ground survey plots.

The data in this resource relates to the other data deliverable resources through the project_id and plot_id fields.
]]></content>
    <id>http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/vegetation-data-aerial-survey-plots-functional-groups-land-cover-mapping-north-slope-of-the-arctic-national-wildlife-refuge-alaska-2019.html</id>
  </entry><entry>
    <title>Total and aqueous arsenic concentrations, physiochemical characteristics, and ancillary data of groundwater from newly constructed drinking water wells in central, northwest, and northeast Minnesota, 2014 – 2016, version 2.0, July 2018</title>
    <link href="http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/total-and-aqueous-arsenic-concentrations-physiochemical-characteristics-and-ancillary-data-of-groundwater-from-newly-constructed-drinking-water-wells-in-central-northwest-and-northeast-minnesota-2014-2016-version-2.0-july-2018.html"/>
    <updated>2021-02-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <content><![CDATA[This dataset provides well construction information provided by driller well logs. Well logs can be accessed on the Minnesota Well Index online (http://www.health.state.mn.us/ divs/eh/cwi/).
]]></content>
    <id>http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/total-and-aqueous-arsenic-concentrations-physiochemical-characteristics-and-ancillary-data-of-groundwater-from-newly-constructed-drinking-water-wells-in-central-northwest-and-northeast-minnesota-2014-2016-version-2.0-july-2018.html</id>
  </entry><entry>
    <title>Taxonomic voucher specimen data from ground and aerial vegetation surveys - Land Cover Mapping, North Slope of the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge, Alaska, 2019</title>
    <link href="http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/taxonomic-voucher-specimen-data-from-ground-and-aerial-vegetation-surveys-land-cover-mapping-north-slope-of-the-arctic-national-wildlife-refuge-alaska-2019.html"/>
    <updated>2021-02-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <content><![CDATA[The resource contains the vegetation voucher specimen data from the ABR, Inc. – Environmental Research and Services (ABR) 2019 ground surveys plots. A few specimens are included from the aerial surveys.

The data in this resource relates to all other data deliverable resources through the project_id and plot_id fields. The data in this resource relate specifically to the data in the file “abr_anwr_ns_lc_veg_cover_deliverable.csv” on the project_id, plot_id, and veg_taxonomy fields.
]]></content>
    <id>http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/taxonomic-voucher-specimen-data-from-ground-and-aerial-vegetation-surveys-land-cover-mapping-north-slope-of-the-arctic-national-wildlife-refuge-alaska-2019.html</id>
  </entry><entry>
    <title>Survey plot data - Land Cover Mapping, North Slope of the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge, Alaska, 2019</title>
    <link href="http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/survey-plot-data-land-cover-mapping-north-slope-of-the-arctic-national-wildlife-refuge-alaska-2019.html"/>
    <updated>2021-02-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <content><![CDATA[The resource contains general plot data, including location data (lat/long) from the ABR, Inc. – Environmental Research and Services (ABR) 2019 ground and aerial surveys, the 2013 Alaska Ecoscience Hula Hula &amp;amp; Dalton Hwy dataset, and the 1987-1992 U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service plots from Jorgenson et al. (1994). Location data are missing for some plots in the Jorgenson et al. (1994), and this is how we received the data.

The data in this resource relates to the other data deliverable resources through the project_id and plot_id fields.
]]></content>
    <id>http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/survey-plot-data-land-cover-mapping-north-slope-of-the-arctic-national-wildlife-refuge-alaska-2019.html</id>
  </entry><entry>
    <title>Soil sample data - Land Cover Mapping, North Slope of the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge, Alaska, 2019</title>
    <link href="http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/soil-sample-data-land-cover-mapping-north-slope-of-the-arctic-national-wildlife-refuge-alaska-2019.html"/>
    <updated>2021-02-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <content><![CDATA[The resource contains soil sample data from the ABR, Inc. – Environmental Research and Services (ABR) 2019 ground surveys.

The data in this resource relates to all other data deliverable resources through the project_id and plot_id fields.  The data in this resource relates specifically to the data in the files “abr_anwr_ns_lc_soil_horizon_deliverable.csv” and “abr_anwr_ns_lc_ssl_data_deliverable.csv” through the project_id, plot_id, and horizon_number fields.
]]></content>
    <id>http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/soil-sample-data-land-cover-mapping-north-slope-of-the-arctic-national-wildlife-refuge-alaska-2019.html</id>
  </entry><entry>
    <title>Soil lab analysis data - Land Cover Mapping, North Slope of the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge, Alaska, 2019</title>
    <link href="http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/soil-lab-analysis-data-land-cover-mapping-north-slope-of-the-arctic-national-wildlife-refuge-alaska-2019.html"/>
    <updated>2021-02-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <content><![CDATA[The resource contains soil lab data from the ABR, Inc. – Environmental Research and Services (ABR) 2019 ground surveys.

The data in this resource relates to all other data deliverable resources through the project_id and plot_id fields.  The data in this resource relates specifically to the data in the files “abr_anwr_ns_lc_soil_horizon_deliverable.csv” and “abr_anwr_ns_lc_soil_sample_deliverable.csv” through the project_id, plot_id, and horizon_number fields. This resource contains the data from the 18-381_csu_lab_data.xlsx and Original_OSU_anwr_lab_data.xlsx in a relational database format.
]]></content>
    <id>http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/soil-lab-analysis-data-land-cover-mapping-north-slope-of-the-arctic-national-wildlife-refuge-alaska-2019.html</id>
  </entry><entry>
    <title>Soil horizon data - Land Cover Mapping, North Slope of the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge, Alaska, 2019</title>
    <link href="http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/soil-horizon-data-land-cover-mapping-north-slope-of-the-arctic-national-wildlife-refuge-alaska-2019.html"/>
    <updated>2021-02-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <content><![CDATA[The resource contains soil horizon data from the ABR, Inc. – Environmental Research and Services (ABR) 2019 ground surveys.

The data in this resource relates to all other data deliverable resources through the project_id and plot_id fields.  The data in this resource relates specifically to the data in the files “abr_anwr_ns_lc_soil_sample_deliverable.csv” and “abr_anwr_ns_lc_ssl_data_deliverable.csv” through the project_id, plot_id, and horizon_number fields.
]]></content>
    <id>http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/soil-horizon-data-land-cover-mapping-north-slope-of-the-arctic-national-wildlife-refuge-alaska-2019.html</id>
  </entry><entry>
    <title>Segment interpretation and validation data - Land Cover Mapping, North Slope of the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge, Alaska, 2019</title>
    <link href="http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/segment-interpretation-and-validation-data-land-cover-mapping-north-slope-of-the-arctic-national-wildlife-refuge-alaska-2019.html"/>
    <updated>2021-02-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <content><![CDATA[The field data and WorldView imagery were leveraged to generate an extensive set of segments labeled with land cover class. These segment interpretations provided the training and validation data for the mapping. Analysts reviewed each aerial and ground plot from the 2019 field survey, examining the plot center and training polygon over the WorldView mosaic, and reviewing field photos, cover estimates, and notes. For each plot, one image segment was identified as the primary example of the vegetation type of the plot (unless there was no suitable example segment, as in cases when a ground plot was targeting a small but distinct vegetation patch that was not captured in the image segmentation). Usually, the primary segment included or was close to the nominal plot center, but this was not always the case, since the target area for the aerial plots could encompass several segments.

After identifying a primary segment, the analyst also identified a set of 0–15 secondary segments that were good examples of the same vegetation type. This assessment was informed by field experience, review of field photos of the landscape setting, and photo-interpretation of the WorldView mosaic.

An additional set of auxiliary segments were identified and assigned to a land cover class. The first set of auxiliary segments was assigned to non-vegetated classes such as lakes, ponds, ocean, barrens, and snowfields or aufeis. While a limited effort was expended to sample such classes during field work, we knew that these would be readily identifiable with high confidence from the WorldView imagery and so focused the field sampling on vegetated classes.

Later, after reviewing preliminary models and receiving feedback from Janet Jorgenson (retired plant ecologist for the Arctic Refuge), we added additional auxiliary segments for vegetated classes based on expert photo interpretation. These were designed to provide the model with additional training data to define the breakpoints between similar classes.

Land cover classes were assigned to all of the primary, secondary, and auxiliary segments. 20% of the segments were randomly selected to be withheld from model training. The final model was validated using the reserved validation segment interpretation points (20% of the full set). These segments were not used to develop the model. The map class was extracted from the final land cover map for each validation point. A confusion matrix, overall accuracy metrics, and per-class performance metrics were calculated from the validation data.
]]></content>
    <id>http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/segment-interpretation-and-validation-data-land-cover-mapping-north-slope-of-the-arctic-national-wildlife-refuge-alaska-2019.html</id>
  </entry><entry>
    <title>Priority Resources of Concern for Stillwater National Wildlife Refuge Complex - Data Documentation</title>
    <link href="http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/priority-resources-of-concern-for-stillwater-national-wildlife-refuge-complex-data-documentation.html"/>
    <updated>2021-02-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <content><![CDATA[A collection of data serving as documentation of Stillwater National Wildlife Refuge Complex priority resources of concern.
]]></content>
    <id>http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/priority-resources-of-concern-for-stillwater-national-wildlife-refuge-complex-data-documentation.html</id>
  </entry><entry>
    <title>points, transects, beach width Barrier island geomorphology and shorebird habitat metrics at 50-m alongshore transects and 5-m cross-shore points Rockaway Peninsula, NY, 2013–2014</title>
    <link href="http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/points-transects-beach-width-barrier-island-geomorphology-and-shorebird-habitat-metrics-at-50-m-alongshore-transects-and-5-m-cross-shore-points-rockaway-peninsula-ny-2013-2014.html"/>
    <updated>2021-02-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <content><![CDATA[Understanding how sea-level rise will affect coastal landforms and the species and habitats they support is critical for crafting approaches that balance the needs of humans and native species. Given this increasing need to forecast sea-level rise effects on barrier islands in the near and long terms, we are developing Bayesian networks to evaluate and to forecast the cascading effects of sea-level rise on shoreline change, barrier island state, and piping plover habitat availability. We use publicly available data products, such as lidar, orthophotography, and geomorphic feature sets derived from those, to extract metrics of barrier island characteristics at consistent sampling distances. The metrics are then incorporated into predictive models and the training data used to parameterize those models. This data release contains the extracted metrics of barrier island geomorphology and spatial data layers of habitat characteristics that are input to Bayesian networks for piping plover habitat availability and barrier island geomorphology. These datasets and models are being developed for sites along the northeastern coast of the United States. This work is one component of a larger research and management program that seeks to understand and sustain the ecological value, ecosystem services, and habitat suitability of beaches in the face of storm impacts, climate change, and sea-level rise.
]]></content>
    <id>http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/points-transects-beach-width-barrier-island-geomorphology-and-shorebird-habitat-metrics-at-50-m-alongshore-transects-and-5-m-cross-shore-points-rockaway-peninsula-ny-2013-2014.html</id>
  </entry><entry>
    <title>points, transects, beach width Barrier island geomorphology and shorebird habitat metrics at 50-m alongshore transects and 5-m cross-shore points Rockaway Peninsula, NY, 2010–2011</title>
    <link href="http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/points-transects-beach-width-barrier-island-geomorphology-and-shorebird-habitat-metrics-at-50-m-alongshore-transects-and-5-m-cross-shore-points-rockaway-peninsula-ny-2010-2011.html"/>
    <updated>2021-02-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <content><![CDATA[Understanding how sea-level rise will affect coastal landforms and the species and habitats they support is critical for crafting approaches that balance the needs of humans and native species. Given this increasing need to forecast sea-level rise effects on barrier islands in the near and long terms, we are developing Bayesian networks to evaluate and to forecast the cascading effects of sea-level rise on shoreline change, barrier island state, and piping plover habitat availability. We use publicly available data products, such as lidar, orthophotography, and geomorphic feature sets derived from those, to extract metrics of barrier island characteristics at consistent sampling distances. The metrics are then incorporated into predictive models and the training data used to parameterize those models. This data release contains the extracted metrics of barrier island geomorphology and spatial data layers of habitat characteristics that are input to Bayesian networks for piping plover habitat availability and barrier island geomorphology. These datasets and models are being developed for sites along the northeastern coast of the United States. This work is one component of a larger research and management program that seeks to understand and sustain the ecological value, ecosystem services, and habitat suitability of beaches in the face of storm impacts, climate change, and sea-level rise.
]]></content>
    <id>http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/points-transects-beach-width-barrier-island-geomorphology-and-shorebird-habitat-metrics-at-50-m-alongshore-transects-and-5-m-cross-shore-points-rockaway-peninsula-ny-2010-2011.html</id>
  </entry><entry>
    <title>points, transects, beach width Barrier island geomorphology and shorebird habitat metrics at 50-m alongshore transects and 5-m cross-shore points Fire Island, NY, 2014–2015</title>
    <link href="http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/points-transects-beach-width-barrier-island-geomorphology-and-shorebird-habitat-metrics-at-50-m-alongshore-transects-and-5-m-cross-shore-points-fire-island-ny-2014-2015.html"/>
    <updated>2021-02-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <content><![CDATA[Understanding how sea-level rise will affect coastal landforms and the species and habitats they support is critical for crafting approaches that balance the needs of humans and native species. Given this increasing need to forecast sea-level rise effects on barrier islands in the near and long terms, we are developing Bayesian networks to evaluate and to forecast the cascading effects of sea-level rise on shoreline change, barrier island state, and piping plover habitat availability. We use publicly available data products, such as lidar, orthophotography, and geomorphic feature sets derived from those, to extract metrics of barrier island characteristics at consistent sampling distances. The metrics are then incorporated into predictive models and the training data used to parameterize those models. This data release contains the extracted metrics of barrier island geomorphology and spatial data layers of habitat characteristics that are input to Bayesian networks for piping plover habitat availability and barrier island geomorphology. These datasets and models are being developed for sites along the northeastern coast of the United States. This work is one component of a larger research and management program that seeks to understand and sustain the ecological value, ecosystem services, and habitat suitability of beaches in the face of storm impacts, climate change, and sea-level rise.
]]></content>
    <id>http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/points-transects-beach-width-barrier-island-geomorphology-and-shorebird-habitat-metrics-at-50-m-alongshore-transects-and-5-m-cross-shore-points-fire-island-ny-2014-2015.html</id>
  </entry><entry>
    <title>points, transects, beach width Barrier island geomorphology and shorebird habitat metrics at 50-m alongshore transects and 5-m cross-shore points Fire Island, NY, 2010–2011</title>
    <link href="http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/points-transects-beach-width-barrier-island-geomorphology-and-shorebird-habitat-metrics-at-50-m-alongshore-transects-and-5-m-cross-shore-points-fire-island-ny-2010-2011.html"/>
    <updated>2021-02-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <content><![CDATA[Understanding how sea-level rise will affect coastal landforms and the species and habitats they support is critical for crafting approaches that balance the needs of humans and native species. Given this increasing need to forecast sea-level rise effects on barrier islands in the near and long terms, we are developing Bayesian networks to evaluate and to forecast the cascading effects of sea-level rise on shoreline change, barrier island state, and piping plover habitat availability. We use publicly available data products, such as lidar, orthophotography, and geomorphic feature sets derived from those, to extract metrics of barrier island characteristics at consistent sampling distances. The metrics are then incorporated into predictive models and the training data used to parameterize those models. This data release contains the extracted metrics of barrier island geomorphology and spatial data layers of habitat characteristics that are input to Bayesian networks for piping plover habitat availability and barrier island geomorphology. These datasets and models are being developed for sites along the northeastern coast of the United States. This work is one component of a larger research and management program that seeks to understand and sustain the ecological value, ecosystem services, and habitat suitability of beaches in the face of storm impacts, climate change, and sea-level rise.
]]></content>
    <id>http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/points-transects-beach-width-barrier-island-geomorphology-and-shorebird-habitat-metrics-at-50-m-alongshore-transects-and-5-m-cross-shore-points-fire-island-ny-2010-2011.html</id>
  </entry><entry>
    <title>points, transects, beach width Barrier island geomorphology and shorebird habitat metrics at 50-m alongshore transects and 5-m cross-shore points Edwin B. Forsythe NWR, NJ, 2013–2014</title>
    <link href="http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/points-transects-beach-width-barrier-island-geomorphology-and-shorebird-habitat-metrics-at-50-m-alongshore-transects-and-5-m-cross-shore-points-edwin-b.-forsythe-nwr-nj-2013-2014.html"/>
    <updated>2021-02-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <content><![CDATA[Understanding how sea-level rise will affect coastal landforms and the species and habitats they support is critical for crafting approaches that balance the needs of humans and native species. Given this increasing need to forecast sea-level rise effects on barrier islands in the near and long terms, we are developing Bayesian networks to evaluate and to forecast the cascading effects of sea-level rise on shoreline change, barrier island state, and piping plover habitat availability. We use publicly available data products, such as lidar, orthophotography, and geomorphic feature sets derived from those, to extract metrics of barrier island characteristics at consistent sampling distances. The metrics are then incorporated into predictive models and the training data used to parameterize those models. This data release contains the extracted metrics of barrier island geomorphology and spatial data layers of habitat characteristics that are input to Bayesian networks for piping plover habitat availability and barrier island geomorphology. These datasets and models are being developed for sites along the northeastern coast of the United States. This work is one component of a larger research and management program that seeks to understand and sustain the ecological value, ecosystem services, and habitat suitability of beaches in the face of storm impacts, climate change, and sea-level rise.
]]></content>
    <id>http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/points-transects-beach-width-barrier-island-geomorphology-and-shorebird-habitat-metrics-at-50-m-alongshore-transects-and-5-m-cross-shore-points-edwin-b.-forsythe-nwr-nj-2013-2014.html</id>
  </entry><entry>
    <title>points, transects, beach width Barrier island geomorphology and shorebird habitat metrics at 50-m alongshore transects and 5-m cross-shore points Cedar Island, VA, 2013–2014</title>
    <link href="http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/points-transects-beach-width-barrier-island-geomorphology-and-shorebird-habitat-metrics-at-50-m-alongshore-transects-and-5-m-cross-shore-points-cedar-island-va-2013-2014.html"/>
    <updated>2021-02-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <content><![CDATA[Understanding how sea-level rise will affect coastal landforms and the species and habitats they support is critical for crafting approaches that balance the needs of humans and native species. Given this increasing need to forecast sea-level rise effects on barrier islands in the near and long terms, we are developing Bayesian networks to evaluate and to forecast the cascading effects of sea-level rise on shoreline change, barrier island state, and piping plover habitat availability. We use publicly available data products, such as lidar, orthophotography, and geomorphic feature sets derived from those, to extract metrics of barrier island characteristics at consistent sampling distances. The metrics are then incorporated into predictive models and the training data used to parameterize those models. This data release contains the extracted metrics of barrier island geomorphology and spatial data layers of habitat characteristics that are input to Bayesian networks for piping plover habitat availability and barrier island geomorphology. These datasets and models are being developed for sites along the northeastern coast of the United States. This work is one component of a larger research and management program that seeks to understand and sustain the ecological value, ecosystem services, and habitat suitability of beaches in the face of storm impacts, climate change, and sea-level rise.
]]></content>
    <id>http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/points-transects-beach-width-barrier-island-geomorphology-and-shorebird-habitat-metrics-at-50-m-alongshore-transects-and-5-m-cross-shore-points-cedar-island-va-2013-2014.html</id>
  </entry><entry>
    <title>points, transects, beach width Barrier island geomorphology and shorebird habitat metrics at 50-m alongshore transects and 5-m cross-shore points Cedar Island, VA, 2012–2013</title>
    <link href="http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/points-transects-beach-width-barrier-island-geomorphology-and-shorebird-habitat-metrics-at-50-m-alongshore-transects-and-5-m-cross-shore-points-cedar-island-va-2012-2013.html"/>
    <updated>2021-02-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <content><![CDATA[Understanding how sea-level rise will affect coastal landforms and the species and habitats they support is critical for crafting approaches that balance the needs of humans and native species. Given this increasing need to forecast sea-level rise effects on barrier islands in the near and long terms, we are developing Bayesian networks to evaluate and to forecast the cascading effects of sea-level rise on shoreline change, barrier island state, and piping plover habitat availability. We use publicly available data products, such as lidar, orthophotography, and geomorphic feature sets derived from those, to extract metrics of barrier island characteristics at consistent sampling distances. The metrics are then incorporated into predictive models and the training data used to parameterize those models. This data release contains the extracted metrics of barrier island geomorphology and spatial data layers of habitat characteristics that are input to Bayesian networks for piping plover habitat availability and barrier island geomorphology. These datasets and models are being developed for sites along the northeastern coast of the United States. This work is one component of a larger research and management program that seeks to understand and sustain the ecological value, ecosystem services, and habitat suitability of beaches in the face of storm impacts, climate change, and sea-level rise.
]]></content>
    <id>http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/points-transects-beach-width-barrier-island-geomorphology-and-shorebird-habitat-metrics-at-50-m-alongshore-transects-and-5-m-cross-shore-points-cedar-island-va-2012-2013.html</id>
  </entry><entry>
    <title>Oregon Coast NWRC Surface Nesting Seabirds - Aerial Photographic Colony Surveys - 2014 GIS Raw Count Databases</title>
    <link href="http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/oregon-coast-nwrc-surface-nesting-seabirds-aerial-photographic-colony-surveys-2014-gis-raw-count-databases.html"/>
    <updated>2021-02-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <content><![CDATA[This reference archives metadata about the collection of geospatial data which may be stored in a variety of file formats (e.g. shapefile, geodatabase) for the Oregon Coast NWRC: Surface Nesting Seabirds - Aerial Photographic Colony Surveys survey (PRIMR ID: FF01RORG00-002 and FF01RTAR00-002). Early records are not recorded digitally, these counts were done by projecting the slide image and manually counting birds on hardcopy. The metadata file will display where counts were done on hardcopy (analog) as well as those done digitally (GIS). Counts (from photographs) were initially started in 2014 but were not completed until 2020. These geospatial files represent the raw count of seabirds from non-georeferenced images. These raw point counts are not registered to any geospatial coordinates. They only line up with the image from which they were derived, no geospatial coordinates are attached to the raw images. Results of the counts are put through a secondary check and then numbers are entered into the complete Seabird Colony Count Catalog (Database) which can be downloaded from https://ecos.fws.gov/ServCat/Reference/Profile/125358, which is the authoritative source for bird count data collected by the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (USFWS). Oregon Coast National Wildlife Refuge Complex manages an Imagery Program for collecting refuge-wide aerial imagery datasets that are used to monitor nesting seabirds on offshore islands. Aerial flights are generally conducted annually to monitor population status and trends, but the imagery is used for other resource monitoring purposes. Aerial photography has served as the primary means for monitoring populations of nesting seabirds, and the subsequent analysis of long-term seabird colony legacy data in the Pacific Northwest as a regional baseline. The 2014 set of photographs have been used to complete a refuge-wide colony count for 2014, where each photograph has a digital point file (hand count) of nesting seabirds stored in a geodatabase format. Census years include 1988, 1994, 2006, and 2014. Following the completion of the census counts described above, we counted a subsample of Oregon coast colonies using a size- and geographical-based stratified random sampling approach for all other survey years. The subsample was selected based on common murre populations, therefore no inferences can be drawn about Brandtâs cormorants without additional colony subsampling. The subsampling approach was informed by recommendations from bio-statistical experts based on colony size and location. We subsampled 45 colonies, which were counted over time. Including census year counts, our subsample years were 1988, 1994, 1997, 2000, 2003, 2006, 2009, 2012, and 2014. A power analysis for the sampling design recommended for the Protocol Framework indicated that a minimum of 16 common murre within each region needed to be counted each year in order detect an average decline of 3.35% per year over a 15-year period (cumulative 40% decline) with 80% probability. With guidance from two statisticians, we randomly selected 6 small and 9 medium/large colonies per region for a total of 45 colonies to be counted each year to detect changes across the Oregon Coast. For more information about the long-term monitoring of seabirds along the Oregon...]]></content>
    <id>http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/oregon-coast-nwrc-surface-nesting-seabirds-aerial-photographic-colony-surveys-2014-gis-raw-count-databases.html</id>
  </entry><entry>
    <title>Oregon Coast NWRC Surface Nesting Seabirds - Aerial Photographic Colony Surveys - 2012 GIS Raw Count Databases</title>
    <link href="http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/oregon-coast-nwrc-surface-nesting-seabirds-aerial-photographic-colony-surveys-2012-gis-raw-count-databases.html"/>
    <updated>2021-02-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <content><![CDATA[This reference archives metadata about the collection of geospatial data which may be stored in a variety of file formats (e.g. shapefile, geodatabase) for the Oregon Coast NWRC: Surface Nesting Seabirds - Aerial Photographic Colony Surveys survey (PRIMR ID: FF01RORG00-002 and FF01RTAR00-002). Starting in 2012 photographs were taken using digital photography (hand-held camera). Counts (from photographs) were initially started in 2012 but were not completed until 2020. These geospatial files represent the raw count of seabirds from non-georeferenced images. These raw point counts are not registered to any geospatial coordinates. They only line up with the image from which they were derived, no geospatial coordinates are attached to the raw images. Results of the counts are put through a secondary check and then numbers are entered into the complete Seabird Colony Count Catalog (Database) which can be downloaded from https://ecos.fws.gov/ServCat/Reference/Profile/125358, which is the authoritative source for bird count data collected by the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (USFWS). Oregon Coast National Wildlife Refuge Complex manages an Imagery Program for collecting refuge-wide aerial imagery datasets that are used to monitor nesting seabirds on offshore islands. Aerial flights are generally conducted annually to monitor population status and trends, but the imagery is used for other resource monitoring purposes. Aerial photography has served as the primary means for monitoring populations of nesting seabirds (Census years include 1988, 1994, 2006, and 2014), and the subsequent analysis of long-term seabird colony legacy data in the Pacific Northwest as a regional baseline. The 2012 set of photographs have been used to complete a refuge-wide colony subsample count for 2012, where each photograph in the subsample has a digital point file (hand count) of nesting seabirds stored in a geodatabase format. We counted a subsample of Oregon coast colonies using a size- and geographical-based stratified random sampling approach for all other survey years. The subsample was selected based on common murre populations, therefore no inferences can be drawn about Brandtâs cormorants without additional colony subsampling. The subsampling approach was informed by recommendations from bio-statistical experts based on colony size and location. We subsampled 45 colonies, which were counted over time. Including census year counts, our subsample years were 1988, 1994, 1997, 2000, 2003, 2006, 2009, 2012, and 2014. A power analysis for the sampling design recommended for the Protocol Framework indicated that a minimum of 16 common murre within each region needed to be counted each year in order detect an average decline of 3.35% per year over a 15-year period (cumulative 40% decline) with 80% probability. With guidance from two statisticians, we randomly selected 6 small and 9 medium/large colonies per region for a total of 45 colonies to be counted each year to detect changes across the Oregon Coast. For more information about the long-term monitoring of seabirds along the Oregon Coast, go to The Service Catalog (ServCat) at the following link: https://ecos.fws.gov/ServCat/Reference/Profile/125347
]]></content>
    <id>http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/oregon-coast-nwrc-surface-nesting-seabirds-aerial-photographic-colony-surveys-2012-gis-raw-count-databases.html</id>
  </entry><entry>
    <title>Oregon Coast NWRC Surface Nesting Seabirds - Aerial Photographic Colony Surveys - 2009 GIS Raw Count Databases</title>
    <link href="http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/oregon-coast-nwrc-surface-nesting-seabirds-aerial-photographic-colony-surveys-2009-gis-raw-count-databases.html"/>
    <updated>2021-02-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <content><![CDATA[This reference archives metadata about the collection of geospatial data which may be stored in a variety of file formats (e.g. shapefile, geodatabase) for the Oregon Coast NWRC: Surface Nesting Seabirds - Aerial Photographic Colony Surveys survey (PRIMR ID: FF01RORG00-002 and FF01RTAR00-002). Starting in 2009 photographs were taken using digital photography (hand-held camera). Counts (from photographs) were initially started in 2009 but were not completed until 2020. These geospatial files represent the raw count of seabirds from non-georeferenced images. These raw point counts are not registered to any geospatial coordinates. They only line up with the image from which they were derived, no geospatial coordinates are attached to the raw images. Results of the counts are put through a secondary check and then numbers are entered into the complete Seabird Colony Count Catalog (Database) which can be downloaded from https://ecos.fws.gov/ServCat/Reference/Profile/125358, which is the authoritative source for bird count data collected by the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (USFWS). Oregon Coast National Wildlife Refuge Complex manages an Imagery Program for collecting refuge-wide aerial imagery datasets that are used to monitor nesting seabirds on offshore islands. Aerial flights are generally conducted annually to monitor population status and trends, but the imagery is used for other resource monitoring purposes. Aerial photography has served as the primary means for monitoring populations of nesting seabirds (Census years include 1988, 1994, 2006, and 2014), and the subsequent analysis of long-term seabird colony legacy data in the Pacific Northwest as a regional baseline. The 2009 set of photographs have been used to complete a refuge-wide colony subsample count for 2009, where each photograph in the subsample has a digital point file (hand count) of nesting seabirds stored in a geodatabase format. We counted a subsample of Oregon coast colonies using a size- and geographical-based stratified random sampling approach for all other survey years. The subsample was selected based on common murre populations, therefore no inferences can be drawn about Brandtâs cormorants without additional colony subsampling. The subsampling approach was informed by recommendations from bio-statistical experts based on colony size and location. We subsampled 45 colonies, which were counted over time. Including census year counts, our subsample years were 1988, 1994, 1997, 2000, 2003, 2006, 2009, 2012, and 2014. A power analysis for the sampling design recommended for the Protocol Framework indicated that a minimum of 16 common murre within each region needed to be counted each year in order detect an average decline of 3.35% per year over a 15-year period (cumulative 40% decline) with 80% probability. With guidance from two statisticians, we randomly selected 6 small and 9 medium/large colonies per region for a total of 45 colonies to be counted each year to detect changes across the Oregon Coast. For more information about the long-term monitoring of seabirds along the Oregon Coast, go to The Service Catalog (ServCat) at the following link: https://ecos.fws.gov/ServCat/Reference/Profile/125347
]]></content>
    <id>http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/oregon-coast-nwrc-surface-nesting-seabirds-aerial-photographic-colony-surveys-2009-gis-raw-count-databases.html</id>
  </entry><entry>
    <title>Oregon Coast NWRC Surface Nesting Seabirds - Aerial Photographic Colony Surveys - 2006 GIS Raw Count Databases</title>
    <link href="http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/oregon-coast-nwrc-surface-nesting-seabirds-aerial-photographic-colony-surveys-2006-gis-raw-count-databases.html"/>
    <updated>2021-02-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <content><![CDATA[This reference archives metadata about the collection of geospatial data which may be stored in a variety of file formats (e.g. shapefile, geodatabase) for the Oregon Coast NWRC: Surface Nesting Seabirds - Aerial Photographic Colony Surveys survey (PRIMR ID: FF01RORG00-002 and FF01RTAR00-002). Early records are not recorded digitally, these counts were done by projecting the slide image and manually counting birds on hardcopy. The metadata file will display where counts were done on hardcopy (analog) as well as those done digitally (GIS). Counts (from photographs) were initially started in 2006 but were not completed until 2020. These geospatial files represent the raw count of seabirds from non-georeferenced images. These raw point counts are not registered to any geospatial coordinates. They only line up with the image from which they were derived, no geospatial coordinates are attached to the raw images. Results of the counts are put through a secondary check and then numbers are entered into the complete Seabird Colony Count Catalog (Database) which can be downloaded from https://ecos.fws.gov/ServCat/Reference/Profile/125358, which is the authoritative source for bird count data collected by the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (USFWS). Oregon Coast National Wildlife Refuge Complex manages an Imagery Program for collecting refuge-wide aerial imagery datasets that are used to monitor nesting seabirds on offshore islands. Aerial flights are generally conducted annually to monitor population status and trends, but the imagery is used for other resource monitoring purposes. Aerial photography has served as the primary means for monitoring populations of nesting seabirds, and the subsequent analysis of long-term seabird colony legacy data in the Pacific Northwest as a regional baseline. The 2006 set of photographs have been used to complete a refuge-wide colony count for 2006, where each photograph has a digital point file (hand count) of nesting seabirds stored in a geodatabase format. Census years include 1988, 1994, 2006, and 2014. Following the completion of the census counts described above, we counted a subsample of Oregon coast colonies using a size- and geographical-based stratified random sampling approach for all other survey years. The subsample was selected based on common murre populations, therefore no inferences can be drawn about Brandtâs cormorants without additional colony subsampling. The subsampling approach was informed by recommendations from bio-statistical experts based on colony size and location. We subsampled 45 colonies, which were counted over time. Including census year counts, our subsample years were 1988, 1994, 1997, 2000, 2003, 2006, 2009, 2012, and 2014. A power analysis for the sampling design recommended for the Protocol Framework indicated that a minimum of 16 common murre within each region needed to be counted each year in order detect an average decline of 3.35% per year over a 15-year period (cumulative 40% decline) with 80% probability. With guidance from two statisticians, we randomly selected 6 small and 9 medium/large colonies per region for a total of 45 colonies to be counted each year to detect changes across the Oregon Coast. For more information about the long-term monitoring of seabirds along the Oregon...]]></content>
    <id>http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/oregon-coast-nwrc-surface-nesting-seabirds-aerial-photographic-colony-surveys-2006-gis-raw-count-databases.html</id>
  </entry><entry>
    <title>Oregon Coast NWRC Surface Nesting Seabirds - Aerial Photographic Colony Surveys - 2003 GIS Raw Count Databases</title>
    <link href="http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/oregon-coast-nwrc-surface-nesting-seabirds-aerial-photographic-colony-surveys-2003-gis-raw-count-databases.html"/>
    <updated>2021-02-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <content><![CDATA[This reference archives metadata about the collection of geospatial data which may be stored in a variety of file formats (e.g. shapefile, geodatabase) for the Oregon Coast NWRC: Surface Nesting Seabirds - Aerial Photographic Colony Surveys survey (PRIMR ID: FF01RORG00-002 and FF01RTAR00-002). Early records are not recorded digitally, these counts were done by projecting the slide image and manually counting birds on hardcopy. The metadata file will display where counts were done on hardcopy (analog) as well as those done digitally (GIS). Counts (from photographs) were initially started in 2003 but were not completed until 2020. These geospatial files represent the raw count of seabirds from non-georeferenced images. These raw point counts are not registered to any geospatial coordinates. They only line up with the image from which they were derived, no geospatial coordinates are attached to the raw images. Results of the counts are put through a secondary check and then numbers are entered into the complete Seabird Colony Count Catalog (Database) which can be downloaded from https://ecos.fws.gov/ServCat/Reference/Profile/125358, which is the authoritative source for bird count data collected by the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (USFWS). Oregon Coast National Wildlife Refuge Complex manages an Imagery Program for collecting refuge-wide aerial imagery datasets that are used to monitor nesting seabirds on offshore islands. Aerial flights are generally conducted annually to monitor population status and trends, but the imagery is used for other resource monitoring purposes. Aerial photography has served as the primary means for monitoring populations of nesting seabirds (Census years include 1988, 1994, 2006, and 2014), and the subsequent analysis of long-term seabird colony legacy data in the Pacific Northwest as a regional baseline. The 2003 set of photographs have been used to complete a refuge-wide colony subsample count for 2003, where each photograph in the subsample has a digital point file (hand count) of nesting seabirds stored in a geodatabase format. We counted a subsample of Oregon coast colonies using a size- and geographical-based stratified random sampling approach for all other survey years. The subsample was selected based on common murre populations, therefore no inferences can be drawn about Brandtâs cormorants without additional colony subsampling. The subsampling approach was informed by recommendations from bio-statistical experts based on colony size and location. We subsampled 45 colonies, which were counted over time. Including census year counts, our subsample years were 1988, 1994, 1997, 2000, 2003, 2006, 2009, 2012, and 2014. A power analysis for the sampling design recommended for the Protocol Framework indicated that a minimum of 16 common murre within each region needed to be counted each year in order detect an average decline of 3.35% per year over a 15-year period (cumulative 40% decline) with 80% probability. With guidance from two statisticians, we randomly selected 6 small and 9 medium/large colonies per region for a total of 45 colonies to be counted each year to detect changes across the Oregon Coast. For more information about the long-term monitoring of seabirds along the Oregon Coast, go to The Service...]]></content>
    <id>http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/oregon-coast-nwrc-surface-nesting-seabirds-aerial-photographic-colony-surveys-2003-gis-raw-count-databases.html</id>
  </entry><entry>
    <title>Oregon Coast NWRC Surface Nesting Seabirds - Aerial Photographic Colony Surveys - 2000 GIS Raw Count Databases</title>
    <link href="http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/oregon-coast-nwrc-surface-nesting-seabirds-aerial-photographic-colony-surveys-2000-gis-raw-count-databases.html"/>
    <updated>2021-02-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <content><![CDATA[This reference archives metadata about the collection of geospatial data which may be stored in a variety of file formats (e.g. shapefile, geodatabase) for the Oregon Coast NWRC: Surface Nesting Seabirds - Aerial Photographic Colony Surveys survey (PRIMR ID: FF01RORG00-002 and FF01RTAR00-002). Early records are not recorded digitally, these counts were done by projecting the slide image and manually counting birds on hardcopy. The metadata file will display where counts were done on hardcopy (analog) as well as those done digitally (GIS). Counts (from photographs) were initially started in 2000 but were not completed until 2020. These geospatial files represent the raw count of seabirds from non-georeferenced images. These raw point counts are not registered to any geospatial coordinates. They only line up with the image from which they were derived, no geospatial coordinates are attached to the raw images. Results of the counts are put through a secondary check and then numbers are entered into the complete Seabird Colony Count Catalog (Database) which can be downloaded from https://ecos.fws.gov/ServCat/Reference/Profile/125358, which is the authoritative source for bird count data collected by the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service (USFWS). Oregon Coast National Wildlife Refuge Complex manages an Imagery Program for collecting refuge-wide aerial imagery datasets that are used to monitor nesting seabirds on offshore islands. Aerial flights are generally conducted annually to monitor population status and trends, but the imagery is used for other resource monitoring purposes. Aerial photography has served as the primary means for monitoring populations of nesting seabirds (Census years include 1988, 1994, 2006, and 2014), and the subsequent analysis of long-term seabird colony legacy data in the Pacific Northwest as a regional baseline. The 2000 set of photographs have been used to complete a refuge-wide colony subsample count for 2000, where each photograph in the subsample has a digital point file (hand count) of nesting seabirds stored in a geodatabase format. We counted a subsample of Oregon coast colonies using a size- and geographical-based stratified random sampling approach for all other survey years. The subsample was selected based on common murre populations, therefore no inferences can be drawn about Brandtâs cormorants without additional colony subsampling. The subsampling approach was informed by recommendations from bio-statistical experts based on colony size and location. We subsampled 45 colonies, which were counted over time. Including census year counts, our subsample years were 1988, 1994, 1997, 2000, 2003, 2006, 2009, 2012, and 2014. A power analysis for the sampling design recommended for the Protocol Framework indicated that a minimum of 16 common murre within each region needed to be counted each year in order detect an average decline of 3.35% per year over a 15-year period (cumulative 40% decline) with 80% probability. With guidance from two statisticians, we randomly selected 6 small and 9 medium/large colonies per region for a total of 45 colonies to be counted each year to detect changes across the Oregon Coast. For more information about the long-term monitoring of seabirds along the Oregon Coast, go to The Service...]]></content>
    <id>http://apievangelist.com/2021/02/25/oregon-coast-nwrc-surface-nesting-seabirds-aerial-photographic-colony-surveys-2000-gis-raw-count-databases.html</id>
  </entry>
</feed>
